Abram P. T. Elder Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Abram P. T. Elder Papers 1890-1916 1903-1916
MSS58594
Elder, Abram P. T. (Abram Peter Turner)
3,280 items
11 containers plus 1 oversize
5 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Biographer and publisher. Correspondence, biographical files, business records of the National Biographical Society, illustrated materials, photographs, and other papers pertaining primarily to Elder's creation and publication of biographical directories for the society.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Chickering, Charles F., 1827-1891.; Corcoran, W. W. (William Wilson), 1798-1888.; Currier, Moody, 1806-1898.; Du Pont, H. A. (Henry Algernon), 1838-1926.; Eddy, Mary Baker, 1821-1910.; Elder, Abram P. T. (Abram Peter Turner); Emerson, Isaac E. (Isaac Edward), 1859-1931.; Fairbanks, Charles W. (Charles Warren), 1852-1918.; Field, Marshall, 1834-1906.; Fleischmann, Julius, 1872-1925.; Grant, Ulysses S., 1852-1929.; Grosvenor, Charles Henry, 1833-1917. Book of the presidents, with biographical sketches. 1902.; Guggenheim, Solomon R. (Solomon Robert), 1861-1949.; Guggenheim, William, 1868-1941.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1837-1904.; Hershey, David N., 1818-; Heurich, Christian, 1842-1945.; Huntington, Henry Edwards, 1850-1927.; Kellogg, Charles, 1825-1892.; Knowles, Henry Miles, 1850-1903.; Lamont, Daniel Scott, 1851-1905.; Lippincott, Craige, 1846-1911.; Longworth, Nicholas, 1869-1931.; McCormick, Cyrus Hall, 1809-1884.; Mills, Darius O. (Darius Ogden), 1825-1910.; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913.; Morton, Levi P. (Levi Parsons), 1824-1920.; Muhlhauser, Gottlieb, 1836-; Newlands, Francis G. (Francis Griffith), 1848-1917.; Pullman, George Mortimer, 1831-1897.; Quay, Matthew Stanley, 1833-1904.
Organizations
National Biographical Society (Washington, D.C.) National Biographical Society (Washington, D.C.) records.; Panama-Pacific International Exposition (1915: San Francisco, Calif.)
Subjects
Capitalists and financiers--Biography.; Directories.; Exhibitions--California--San Francisco.; Philanthropists--United States--Biography.; Politicians--United States--Biography.; Presidents--United States--Biography.; Publishers and publishing--United States.
Places
Middletown (R.I.)--History.
Occupations
Biographers.; Publishers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Abram P. T. Elder, biographer and publisher, were given to the Library of Congress by Elder's daughter, Althea Elder, in 1979.
Access and Restrictions
The Elder Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
circa 1890 Married Emma Elizabeth Householder (died 1945)
1896 Coauthored with E. H. Elder The Light of the World: Or Our Savior in Art. Chicago: Elder Co. (Republished London, New York: British-American Co., 1899)
1902 1903 Published Charles H. Grosvenor's The Book of the Presidents, with Biographical Sketches. Washington, D.C.: Continental Press
circa 1903 1912 Published biographical directories entitled The National Memorial of the United States
circa 1930 Died, California
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Abram Peter Turner Elder (circa 1890-circa 1930) span the years 1890-1916, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1903-1916, and include correspondence, illustrated material, photographs, biographical files, and miscellaneous matter. The collection is divided into three series: Correspondence, Biographical Case Files, and Miscellany.
Little is known of Elder's life or career outside the professional associations and productions illuminated by his papers, other than that he was involved in creating and marketing specialty publications. In 1896 Elder and a relative published a compendium of religious art, apparently marketed by private subscriptions and published by a family corporation in Chicago. In 1899 they reissued the book through a worldwide publishing firm. There is no information, however, in the Elder Papers concerning these ventures. In 1902 Charles H. Grosvenor began compiling The Book of the Presidents, with Biographical Sketches, a customized biographical directory for sale by private subscription. The National Biographical Society, a commercial firm of which Elder was an official, became involved in Grosvenor's work, eventually assuming control of most or all aspects of its publication, which is noted in correspondence in the Elder Papers and is graphically represented in four-color engravings of title sheets, sample page proofs, and other publishing matter.
Between approximately 1903 and 1912, Elder assisted in the preparation of another customized biographical directory, marketed via subscription and published under the auspices of his firm, entitled The National Memorial of the United States. Correspondence and related records in Elder's papers provide an in-depth view of the efforts to publish the National Memorial, with extensive detail concerning contracts, quality of work which printing firms promised or submitted, internal personnel matters, efforts to identify a subscriber audience and increase sales, and outreach, including an award-winning exhibit in the Panama-Pacific International Exposition of 1915-1916 in San Francisco. Most of the correspondence regarding the National Memorial was generated by several officials of the National Biographical Society, including Elder, but was not signed and is impossible or difficult to identify by author. Prominent among the correspondents are society officials Charles H. Grosvenor, Robert E. Doan, Lucy S. Bahnsen, R. E. Montague, and Richard R. McMahon.
The Biographical Case Files contain correspondence, background information, clippings, and other printed matter, as well as photographs and biographical entries regarding the individuals profiled in the National Memorial. Many of the people featured were prominent local, state, and national politicians, capitalists, and philanthropists, including Charles F. Chickering, W. W. Corcoran, Moody Currier, H. A. Du Pont, Mary Baker Eddy, Isaac E. Emerson, Charles W. Fairbanks, Marshall Field, Julius Fleischmann, Ulysses S. Grant II, Solomon R. Guggenheim, William Guggenheim, Edward Everett Hale, Marcus Alonzo Hanna, David N. Hershey, Christian Heurich, Henry Edwards Huntington, Charles Kellogg, Henry Miles Knowles, Daniel Scott Lamont, Craige Lippincott, Nicholas Longworth, Cyrus Hall McCormick, Darius O. Mills, J. Pierpont Morgan, Levi P. Morton, Gottlieb Muhlhauser, Francis G. Newlands, George Mortimer Pullman, and Matthew Stanley Quay.
A small number of records document the organization, function, and mission of the National Biographical Society, including statements of intent, bylaws, articles of incorporation, and sample stockholder certificates. A very small amount of correspondence concerns the maintenance of Elmhyrst, the Elder family summer estate in Middletown, Rhode Island, and is virtually the only reference in this collection to Elder's nonprofessional life.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1897-1916
Biographical Case Files, circa 1890-1916
Miscellany, circa 1902-circa 1916
Oversize
Container List
- Correspondence, 1897-1916 (Box 1-2)
  Letters to and from Elder, Charles H. Grosvenor, Lucy S. Bahnsen, and Richard R. McMahon regarding efforts to publish specialty biographical directories and to promote the National Biographical Society's business.
  Arranged chronologically by year, month, and day.
  - Feb. 1897-Apr. 1904 (Box 1)
  - May 1904-Dec. 1905
  - Aug. 1906-Feb. 1911
  - Mar. 1911-Dec. 1912
  - Jan. 1913-Mar. 1914
  - Apr.-Oct. 1914 (Box 2)
  - Nov. 1914-Feb. 1915
  - Mar.-July 1915
  - Aug. 1915-May 1916, undated
  - Undated
- Biographical Case Files, circa 1890-1916 (Box 3-10)
  Correspondence, background information, photographs, press articles, and other materials regarding the individuals profiled in The National Memorial of the United States.
  Arranged alphabetically by surname of case file subject.
  - Adams-Carter (Box 3)
    - Adams, Alvin
    - Bradford, William Henry
    - Campbell, Felix
    - Carr, Jessie Williamson
    - Carr, Julian Shakespeare
    - Carter, William Thornton
  - Cary-Castree
    - Cary, Richard
    - Casement, James S.
    - Castree, John
  - Chickering-Cleveland
    - Chickering, Charles F.
    - Childs, G. W.
    - Chisholm, William
    - Clark, Alexander S.
    - Clarke, Dumont
    - Cleveland, Merritt A.
  - Cochran-Corcoran
    - Cochran, James Henry
    - Coldewey, Anton F.
    - Conarroe, George Mecum
    - Corbin, Henry Clarke
    - Corcoran, W. W.
  - Corlies-Coxe
    - Corlies, Samuel Fisher
    - Coster, Charles Henry
    - Cotton, John B.
    - Covel, Alphonso S.
    - Coxe, Alexander Brinton
  - Cramp-Croxton
    - Cramp, Charles Henry
    - Crawford, Charles Martin
    - Croxton, John G.
  - Currier
    - Currier, Moody
  - Curtis-Cutting
    - Curtis, John B.
    - Cutting, William Bayard
  - Davis-Dederick
    - Davis, David
    - Davis, Henry Gassaway
    - Dean, Charles Leroy
    - Dederick, P. K.
  - Dennis-De Peyster (Box 4)
    - Dennis, Graham Barclay
  - Denny, Arthur Armstrong
    - Denny, Harman
    - De Peyster, J. Watts
  - Devereux-Dingley
    - Devereux, J. H.
    - Dewhurst, James B.
    - Dexter, Henry
    - De Young, Michael H.
    - Dick, Charles
    - Dickinson, Don M.
    - Dines, Josiah
    - Dingley, Nelson
  - Doane-Douglas
    - Doane, William H.
    - Dodge, David Child
    - Dodge, Henry Lee
    - Douglas, William Harris
  - Dubois-Duffy
    - Dubois, John Ezekiel
    - Duffy, Walter B.
  - Duncan-Dwyer
    - Duncan, Daniel
    - Dunn, William Mckee
    - Du Pont, H. A.
    - Durant, Henry Fowle
  - Duncan-Dwyer
    - Dwyer, Jeremiah
  - Eastman-Eddy
    - Eastman, Joseph
    - Eaton, Benjamin Harrison
    - Eddy, Mary Baker
  - Eells-Emerson
    - Eells, Dan Parmelee
    - Elder, Abram Peter Turner
    - Elkins, Stephen Benton
    - Ellis, John Washington
    - Emerson, Isaac E.
  - Emery-Everard
    - Emery, Lewis, Jr.
    - Emery, Matthew Gault
    - England, Thomas Y.
    - Everard, James
  - Failing-Fanning
    - Failing, Henry
    - Fairbanks, Charles W.
    - Fall, Charles Gershom
    - Fanning, David Hale
  - Farrel-Fay (Box 5)
    - Farrel, Franklin
    - Farwel, Charles B.
    - Farwel, John V.
    - Fay, Frank B.
  - Fell-Fisher
    - Fell, Jesse
    - Ffoulke, Charles Mather
    - Field, Marshall
    - Firestone, Clinton D.
    - Fisher, Newton D.
  - Fleischmann-Foss
    - Fleischmann, Julius
    - Fletcher, Henry E.
    - Fobes, Hiram
    - Foerderer, Robert H.
    - Fort, Greenburg L.
    - Foss, Eugene Noble
  - Freiburg-Frye
    - Freiburg, Julius
    - French, Carlos
    - Fry, Henry D.
    - Frye, William P.
  - Gage-Gayley
    - Gage, Lyman J.
    - Gary, E. H.
    - Gaston, William Alexander
    - Gay, Henry
    - Gayley, James
  - Gibbons-Goddard
    - Gibbons, James
    - Gilman, Daniel Coit
    - Ginn, Edwin
    - Glover, C. C.
    - Goddard, Hiram
    - Goddard, William Henry
  - Goldthwaite-Gould
    - Goldthwaite, George
    - Goodnow, Edward A.
    - Gould, Charles A.
  - Grant-Griffin
    - Grant, Ulysses S., II
    - Greene, Jacob L.
    - Greenhut, Joseph B.
    - Greer, C. H.
    - Greist, John M.
    - Griffin, Eugene
  - Griffith-Griscom
    - Griffith, Frederick W.
    - Griffiths, John L.
    - Grinnell, Frederick
    - Griscom, Clement A.
  - Grosvenor (Box 6)
    - Grosvenor, Ebenezer O.
    - Grosvenor, William
    - Grout-Guggenheim
    - Grout, William L.
    - Guggenheim, Solomon R.
    - Guggenheim, William
  - Haberkorn-Hale
    - Haberkorn, Christian H.
    - Hackley, Charles H.
    - Hague, James D.
    - Hale, Edward Everett
  - Hall-Hanna
    - Hall, Edward J.
    - Hamlin, Henry
    - Hammer, D. Harry
    - Hanna, Henry
    - Hanna, Marcus Alonzo
  - Hardin-Harris
    - Hardin, George A.
    - Harlow, Willis Poe
    - Harriman, Oliver, Jr.
    - Harris, Norman W.
  - Harrison-Harvey
    - Harrison, Lynde
    - Harter, Michael D.
  - Harrison-Harvey
    - Harvey, George B. McClellan
  - Haskell-Hawes
    - Haskell, Horace S.
    - Haven, Franklin
    - Hawes, Kirk
  - Hawley-Hayes
    - Hawley, Jessie G.
    - Hawley, Joseph Roswell
    - Hay, John
    - Hayes, Joel Addison
  - Haynes-Hazen
    - Haynes, John C.
    - Hays, Franklin William
    - Hazeltine, Abram J.
    - Hazen, David Henry
  - Head-Henderson
    - Head, Addison E.
    - Hearst, Phoebe A.
    - Heath, Daniel Collamore
    - Hegeman, John R.
    - Heinze, Arthur Philip
    - Henderson, David B.
    - Henderson, J. B.
  - Hershey-Hill
    - Hershey, David N.
    - Heurich, Christian
    - Hewitt, Henry, Jr.
    - Hicks, Radcliffe
    - Hill, James J.
  - Hitchcock-Horton
    - Hitchcock, Peter M.
    - Hitt, Robert R.
    - Hobart, Garret Augustus
    - Holden, Liberty Emery
    - Holland, John Philip
    - Horton, Harry Lawrence
  - Hotchkiss-Hoyt (Box 7)
    - Hotchkiss, Henry Oaks
    - Houston, H. H.
    - Howard, Edmonds J.
    - Howes, Seth B.
    - Hoyt, Colgate
  - Hubbard-Huff
    - Hubbard, Thomas Hamlin
    - Hudnut, Richard A.
    - Hudson, John E.
    - Huff, George Franklin
  - Huidekoper-Hunt
    - Huidekoper, Frederic Wolters
    - Hulbert, William P.
    - Hull, Calvin E.
    - Hull, Charles J.
    - Hunt, Wilson G.
  - Huntington-Hutchins
    - Huntington, Henry Edwards
    - Hurlbut, Hinman B.
    - Hurst, John E.
    - Hutchins, Stillson
  - Hutton-Irwin
    - Hutton, William Edward
    - Hyde, Louis K.
    - Irwin, Dudley M.
  - Janes-Jenkins
    - Janes, Henry
    - Jarvis, George A.
    - Jay, Willliam
    - Jayne, David
    - Jenkins, James G.
  - Jesup-Jones
    - Jesup, Morris K.
    - Jones, Charles
    - Jones, Fernando
    - Jones, Frank J.
  - Keene-Kendall
    - Keene, James R.
    - Kellogg, Charles
    - Kellogg, William Pitt
    - Kelly, William H.
    - Kempner, H.
    - Kendall, Nathaniel Wyeth
  - Kibbey-Kohler
    - Kibbey, William B.
    - Kilbourne, James
    - Kimball, William S.
    - Kirk, James A.
    - Knabe, William
    - Knowles, Francis B.
    - Knowles, Henry Miles
    - Kohler, Charles
  - Lafean-Lamont
    - Lafean, Daniel F.
    - Laird, William Harris
    - Lamont, Daniel Scott
  - Lane-Law
    - Lane, Henry S.
    - Lanius, William H.
    - Lauterbach, Edward
    - Law, George
    - Law, Hartland
  - Lawrence
    - Lawrence, Mortimer J.
    - Lawrence, William Van Duzer
  - Leaming-Leiter (Box 8)
    - Leaming, Thomas
    - Ledyard, Lewis Cass
    - Lee, Fred E.
    - Leeds, William B.
    - Leeson, Richard L.
    - Leidersdorf, B.
    - Leiter, Levi Z.
  - Lenman-Littauer
    - Lenman, John T.
    - Lewis, George H.
    - Lippincott, Craige
    - Lippitt, Charles Warren
    - Littauer, Lucius N.
  - Logan-Longley
    - Logan, Frank G.
    - Logan, John A.
    - Logan, Walter S.
    - Longley, Charles E.
  - Longworth-Loree
    - Longworth, Nicholas
    - Longyear, John M.
    - Loomis, John Mason
    - Lore, Charles B.
    - Loree, Leonor Fresnel
  - Loudenslayer-Lowe
    - Loudenslayer, Henry C.
    - Lounsbery, Richard P.
    - Lowden, Frank O.
    - Lowe, Arthur H.
  - Lucas-Lunt
    - Lucas, Anthony F.
    - Luce, Stephen B.
    - Lunt, Orrington
  - MacArthur-Manning
    - MacArthur, Arthur
    - Mackay, Clarence H.
    - Magee, Chris L.
    - Manning, Daniel
  - Marie-Marquis
    - Marie, Peter
    - Markle, Alvan
    - Markle, John
    - Marquis, Milton Scott
  - Martin-Matthews
    - Martin, Milton D.
    - Mason, Beverly R.
    - Mason
    - Matthews, Stanley
  - McCall-McCormick
    - McCall, John A.
    - McCord, Warren E.
    - McCormick, Cyrus Hall
  - McCoy-McKim (Box 9)
    - McCoy, Daniel
    - McDermott, Allan, L.
    - McIntosh, David G.
    - McIntyre, Thomas A.
    - McKeen, W. R.
    - McKim, Charles F.
    - McKim, Randolf
  - McWilliams-Merrill
    - McWilliams, Lafayette
    - Mead, Oliver D.
    - Menefee, Flournoy
    - Merrill, Sherburn S.
  - Merritt-Milburn
    - Merritt, H. P.
    - Merritt, John A.
    - Messmer, Sebastian G.
    - Milburn, John G.
  - Miller
    - Miller, Andrew G.
    - Miller, Charles
    - Miller, Conrad
    - Miller, Frederick A.
    - Miller, Lewis
    - Miller, Warner
  - Mills-Mitchell
    - Mills, Anson
    - Mills, Cyrus T.
    - Mills, Darius O.
    - Mitchell, John H.
  - Moerlein-Morton
    - Moerlein, Christian
    - Moore, Edward W.
    - Moore, James H.
    - Morgan, J. Pierpont
    - Morton, Levi P.
    - Morton, Paul
  - Muhlhauser-Murphy
    - Muhlhauser, Gottlieb
    - Murphy, Frank M.
    - Murphy, Franklin
  - Neff-Newlands
    - Neff, Jacob H.
    - Netcher, Charles
    - Nevins, David
    - Newcomb, H. Victor
    - Newhouse, Samuel
    - Newlands, Francis G.
  - Newmyer-Nixon
    - Newmyer, John S.
    - Nichols, Charles H.
    - Nicol, Robert
    - Nixon, Samuel F.
  - Norton-Nunnemacher
    - Norton, Henry B.
    - Noyes, Crosby S.
    - Nunnemacher, Rudolph
  - O'Connell-Orme
    - O'Connell, Monsignor
    - Ogleboy, Earl W.
    - Oglesby, Joseph H.
    - Olmstead, Marlin Edgar
    - Orme, Charles H.
  - Osborne-Otis
    - Osborne, John H.
    - Osgood, Hugh H.
    - Otis, Harrison Gray
    - Otis, Norton P.
  - Palmer-Pardee (Box 10)
    - Palmer, Lowell M.
    - Palmer, Stephen S.
    - Parchen, Henry M.
    - Pardee, George C.
  - Parlin-Payne
    - Parlin, William H.
    - Parsons, John D.
    - Parsons, William Henry
    - Patterson, John H.
    - Patton, Alexander E.
    - Payne, Henry C.
  - Peabody-Perkins
    - Peabody, Arthur J.
    - Peacock, Alex R.
    - Pennypacker, Samuel W.
    - Perkins, George C.
    - Perkins, Lucius H.
  - Phillips-Plankinton
    - Phillips, Duncan C.
    - Phillips, John C.
    - Pillsbury, Charles A.
    - Plankinton, John
  - Platt-Pond
    - Platt, Henry Clay
    - Platt, Orville H.
    - Platt, Thomas C.
    - Powers, Samuel L.
    - Pond, E. B.
  - Poor-Portner
    - Poor, Henry W.
    - Pope, George A.
    - Porter, Washington
    - Portner, Robert
  - Potter-Pullman
    - Potter, Isaac M.
    - Price, Vincent C.
    - Pullman, George Mortimer
  - Quackenbush-Quincy
    - Quackenbush, Peter
    - Quay, Matthew Stanley
    - Quincy, Henry P.
  - Reeves
    - Reeves, David
  - Scattergood-Shober
    - Scattergood, Thomas
    - Schley, Winfield Scott
    - Shober, Samuel L.
  - Shoenberger-Witt
    - Shoenberger, John H.
    - Spaulding, Edward R.
    - Willard, D.
    - Witt, Stillman
  - Untitled
- Miscellany, circa 1902-circa 1916 (Box 11)
  Legal and organizational records of the National Biographical Society, including bylaws and articles of incorporation, marketing advice given to society sales agents, subscriber lists, and sample pages from The Book of the Presidents and The National Memorial of the United States.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Legal and other records (Box 11)
  - Marketing advice to agents
  - Page proofs, title pages, and illustrated matter See Oversize
  - Potential subscribers
  - Subscriber lists
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  Oversize page proofs, title pages, illustrated matter, and other items described according to the series, folder, and boxes from which they were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Page proofs, title pages, illustrated matter, and other material (Container 11)